Finding aid to Marian Parry artwork and papers MRBC.MS.00428
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Marian Parry artwork and papers
approximately 1944-1994
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Parry, Marian
MRBC.MS.00428
12 linear feet (4 record cartons, 2 flat boxes)
Marian Parry is an author, poet, illustrator, and watercolor artist. In addition to her writing and art, Parry was the founder and senior instructor of the Watercolor Program for the Radcliffe Seminars at Harvard University, and would hold speaking engagements across New England. This collection includes publications, sketchbooks, original artwork, and working and concept files from Marian Parry's career. Also includes event posters, poetry magazines, and personal and business correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marian Parry's children, Laura Feld and Andrew Feld, who removed it from her home as part of her downsizing and knew that she wanted it to come to Smith College because of her past connection to Ruth Mortimer.
Biographical / Historical
Marian Parry is an author, poet, illustrator, and watercolor artist. Born in San Francisco in 1924, she spent the first few years of her childhood in Paris, France before her family moved back to the US. After attending the University of California at Berkeley, she relocated to Cambridge, Massachusetts where she spent her career and adult life. In addition to her writing and art, Parry was the founder and senior instructor of the Watercolor Program for the Radcliffe Seminars at Harvard University, and would hold speaking engagements across New England. Though the bulk of her work can be found at the Boston Public Library, it is also on display at the Metropolitan Museum of Art and various rare book collections across the country.
Related Materials
Materials already in the Smith College MRBC: "The Birds/Aristophanes" (885 A7av Efi 1959), "Exercises in Perspective" (NC750.P27), "Liber amicorum" (MS 300), original drawings for "Aristophanes" (MS 266), "Passions" (704.1 P2492p 1979), "The Patagonian stamp magnate: an instruction manual" (MS 265), "Roger and the Devil" (Juv 1972 P249r), "Tendril." (PS615 .T39), " Die Vögel: The Birds of Basle (Eine fast unheimliche Geschichte)" (NC1075.P283 A45)
Related Materials
Materials in the Five College collection: "The Ballad of the Long-Tailed Rat" (UM Juvenile / PZ8.3.P564 Bal), "Fables in Two Languages and Similar Diversions" (AC Frost Stacks / PS3566.R324 F3 1994), "The Paris Book" (AC Frost Stacks / ND2130 .P27 2015), "Tendril." (Five College Annex / PS580 .T4 / Per), "The Zoo Conspiracy" (UM Rudman Childrens Literature Col. / WAR Levin)
Content Description
Publications, sketchbooks, original artwork, and working and concept files from Marian Parry's career. Also includes a 33.5 rpm record of one of her illustrated books and several transparencies.
Sound recordings; Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women artists--History--20th century--Sources; Illustrations; Parry, Marian; Feld, Laura; Feld, Andrew; Feld, Laura; Feld, Andrew
- "Cambridge 1971" artist book (Box 1)
- "Swinging Animal Riddles" artist book (Box 1)
- "Paris" draft book and sketches, 1952 (Box 1)
- "Fin de Siècle Grunge Chic" artist book (Box 1)
- "Some Birds of Congested Passions" artist book, May 17, 1957 (Box 1)
- "Intrigue in the Conservatory" artist book (Box 1)
- "Ornamental Furbelows" artist book, 1985 (Box 1)
- "Venetian Notebook" (2) (Box 1)
- "Au Bon Pain '92" artist book, 1992 (Box 1)
- "Passions" drawings and artist book (unbound), 1979 (Box 1)
- "8 Bostonians" drawings, colophons, watercolor, artist book (Box 1)
- "Lions at Random" artist book, Apr 1983 (Box 1)
- "A Few Women" drawings (Box 1)
- "Swinging Animal Riddles" book draft (Box 1)
- "The Chelsea District" sketches (Box 1)
- "Melodrama in Sepia" 1-6 (Box 1)
- "The Self-Romantic" artist book, Oct 1955 (Box 1)
- "Ch. Eng. N. Fabriano" drawings (Box 1)
- "Reserfiert Für Basler" artist book, 1970 (Box 1)
- "Galashiels" artist book (Box 1)
- "Harvard Square" drawings series (colophons, drafts, woodcut prints, artist books), 1963-1996 (Box 1)
- "A Few Flights of Fashionable Fancy" artist book (Box 1)
- "Harvard Square" and "A Few Flights..." drawings, uncut (Box 1)
- "Romantic Decorations" artist book, Sept 1956 (Box 1)
- "Tottenham Court" drawings (Box 1)
- "Artist Book #1" artist book (Box 1)
- Alphabet prints (Box 1)
- "Scenes in the Salon" artist book, unfinished (Box 1)
- "Insane Animal Book" 5.5x8.5 sketchbook, May 1960 (Box 1)
- "Birds" 5.5x8.5 sketchbook, 1960 (Box 1)
- "FUNG" 5.5x8.5 sketchbook, 1961 (Box 1)
- "The Three Eggs" 5x8 sketchbook, 1960 (Box 1)
- Alexis Drawing 6x8 sketchbook (5), 1956-1958 (Box 1)
- Spirax 6x8 sketchbook, 1962 (Box 1)
- Aquabee Super Deluxe 6x9 sketchbook (2), 1981 (Box 1)
- "Animals" 5x8 sketchbook, 1960 (Box 1)
- "Exercises in perspective" bound sketches, 5x8 sketchbook, 1965 (Box 1)
- "Cambridge" 5x7 sketchbook, February 1967 (Box 1)
- "Cambridge" 9x12 sketchbook, Oct 1966 (Box 1)
- "Des Veus Extraordinaires" 4x6 sketchbook (Box 1)
- "Les Oiseaux d'Aristophane" drawing pad, 1959 (Box 1)
- "Des Animaux" sketchbook, 1958 (Box 1)
- "3" sketchbook, 1956 (Box 1)
- "Basel I" and "Basel II" sketchbooks, 1969 (Box 1)
- "Animals" sketchbook (Box 1)
- "Danaos" drawing pad, July 1953 (Box 1)
- "Mouse epic" 9x12 drawing pad, 1977 (Box 1)
- "Children's Stories etc" 9x12 sketchbook, Nov 29, 1968 (Box 1)
- "The Classic Disciplines" 9x12 sketchbook, Apr 2, 1953 (Box 1)
- "Des Charactèrs" sketchbook (Box 1)
- "Carnival" 5x7 watercolor sketchbook (Box 1)
- "3D3O" sketchbook (Box 1)
- "Notes from site #4" sketchbook (Box 1)
- "I Am a Big Help" sketches and sketch dummy, 1980 (Box 2)
- "The Zoo Conspiracy" sketches, 1973 (Box 2)
- "King of the Fish" sketches, 1977 (Box 2)
- "The Ballad of the Long-Tailed Rat" proofs and sketches, 1975 (Box 2)
- "Fox Stories" drafts and sketch folders ("Crow," "Grapes," "Crane"), 1970 (Box 2)
- "City Mouse - Country Mouse" draft, 1970 (Box 2)
- "The Space Child's Mother Goose" sketches, original artwork, volume II mock-up, and re-issue proofs, 1958-1968 (Box 2)
- "The Fanatic's Ecstatic Aromatic Guide to Onions, Garlic, Shallots, and Leeks" drafts, 1981 (Box 2)
- "The Lazies" sketches, 1973 (Box 2)
- misc sketches from manuscripts (Box 2)
- Drafts and concept art for unpublished works, 1975-1995 (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes art and concepts for "Boxtop," "Ambronius," "Guiomar of the Sea," "Auk! Auk!," "Sebastian and the Fishsquisher," "Fish in the Trees," "Henry's Father's Pig," "First Day," "Two Frogs," "M Is For Mouse," "Basilisk," lion stories and sketches, "Super-Cyclist Cinderella," "Little Known Noises," "Houdini," "Vrai et Raisonable Histoire de la France au XVI Siècle," "Snobs and Slobs"
- "Gossips" translation drafts (Box 3)
- "Fox and the Grapes, and Two More Fox Stories from Aesop" drafts and sketches (Box 3)
- "Onions, Onions, Onions!" drafts and sketches, 1978 (Box 3)
- "Passions" artist book drafts, 1979 (Box 3)
- "King of the Fish" draft, 1977 (Box 3)
- "Paris" draft, 1952 (Box 3)
- "Unnumbered Prints: Book II" (Box 3)
- "The Pleasures of Winter" prints (Box 3)
- "ABC" file (Box 3)
- Alphabet print drafts (Box 3)
- "Coelacanth" drafts and correspondence (Box 3)
- "Renaissance" draft (Box 3)
- "Wicked foxes" drawings (Box 3)
- Rat sketches (Box 3)
  - "Alvarez" (Box 3)
  - "Buoye" (Box 3)
  - "Cuccoli" (Box 3)
  - "Morrison" (Box 3)
- "Demetrios" draft and sketches (Box 3)
- Correspondence and journal pages, 1955-1995 (Box 3)
- Poetry (Box 3)
- Published materials and cards, 1979-1991 (Box 3)
- "Paris" transparencies, 2000 (Box 3)
- Hard-backed watercolor and ink drawings (Box 4)
- Watercolors: wetlands, loose (Box 4)
- Watercolors: miscellaneous (Box 4)
- "Exercise in Perspective" and "Erotic Scene" from the Boston Visual Artists Union Gallery (Box 4)
- Original drawings, sketches, and sketchbook pages (Box 4)
- Miniature watercolors (Box 4)
- Miniature drawings (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
- Portraits (large sketches) (Box 4)
- Portraits (small) (Box 4)
- Journal notes (Box 4)
- Cards and invitations (Box 4)
- "Simpler drawings with color" 1-23 (Box 4)
- "Grand Street Drawings" (Box 4)
- Drawing folders (animals, people, buildings, miscellaneous) (Box 4)
- Germany (Basel) sketches, 1969 (Box 4)
- Labels for Parry's work when exhibited (Box 4)
- "King of the Fish" mock-up, 1977 (Box 5)
- "Ballad of the Long-Tailed Rat" mock-up, 1975 (Box 5)
- "I Am A Big Help" mock-up, 1980 (Box 6)
- Radcliffe Quarterly magazine cover draft, December 1974 (Box 6)
- "City Mouse - Country Mouse" mock-up, 1970 (Box 6)
- "The Lazies" mock-up, 1973 (Box 6)
- "The Fanatic's Ecstatic Aromatic Guide to Onions, Garlic, Shallots, and Leeks" mock-up, 1981 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous oversize (Box 6)
- "Serbian Ballad" (unfinished) (Box 6)